I have a question.
لدي سؤال.
Can a computer write poetry?
هل يستطيع الكمبيوتر كتابة الشعر؟
This is a provocative question.
هذا سؤال استفزازي.
You think about it for a minute,
تفكر في إجابة له لمدة دقيقة،
and you suddenly have a bunch of other questions like:
وسيتبادر إليك فجأة مجموعة أخرى من الأسئلة مثل:
What is a computer?
ما هو الكمبيوتر؟
What is poetry?
ما هو الشعر؟
What is creativity?
ما هو الإبداع؟
But these are questions
ولكن هذه أسئلة
that people spend their entire lifetime trying to answer,
يقضي الناس معظم حياتهم في محاولة للإجابة عليها.
not in a single TED Talk.
وليس في محادثة TED واحدة.
So we're going to have to try a different approach.
لذا سنحاولة اتباع منهاج مختلفا.
So up here, we have two poems.
لدينا هنا قصيدتان.
One of them is written by a human,
واحدة كتبها إنسان،
and the other one's written by a computer.
والأخرى كتبها حاسوب.
I'm going to ask you to tell me which one's which.
سأطلب منكم تحديد من كتب كل واحدة منها.
Have a go:
لنبدأ:
Poem 1: Little Fly / Thy summer's play, / My thoughtless hand / Has brush'd away.
قصيدة 1: ذبابة صغيرة / ألعاب الصيف، / يدي الطائشة / قد مرت بعيدة.
Am I not / A fly like thee? / Or art not thou / A man like me?
ألست أنا / ذبابة مثلك؟ / أو الفن ليس أنت / رجل مثلي؟
Poem 2: We can feel / Activist through your life's / morning /
قصيدة 2: يمكن أن نشعر / بالنشاط خلال حياتك / الصباحية /
Pauses to see, pope I hate the / Non all the night to start a / great otherwise (...)
توقف لرؤية، بابا أنا أكره / ليست كل ليلة لبدء / خلاف عظيم (...)
Alright, time's up.
حسنًا انتهى الوقت.
Hands up if you think Poem 1 was written by a human.
أرفعوا أيديكم إن كنتم تعتقدون أن القصيدة 1 كتبها إنسان.
OK, most of you.
حسنًا، معظمكم.
Hands up if you think Poem 2 was written by a human.
رفعوا أيديكم إن كنتم تعتقدون أن القصيدة 2 كتبها إنسان.
Very brave of you,
شجاعة كبيرة منكم،
because the first one was written by the human poet William Blake.
لأن القصيدة الأولى كُتبت من قبل شاعر يدعى وليان بليك.
The second one was written by an algorithm
أما الثانية كُتبت بالاستعانة بخوارزمية
that took all the language from my Facebook feed on one day
التي تقوم باستخرج كل الكلام من المستجدات الموجودة على حساب الفيس بوك الخاص بي
and then regenerated it algorithmically,
ومن ثم تعيد كتابتها باستخدام خوارزميات،
according to methods that I'll describe a little bit later on.
وفقاً لأساليب سأشرحها لكم لاحقًا.
So let's try another test.
لذا لنقم باختبار آخر.
Again, you haven't got ages to read this,
مرة أخرى، لن تحصلوا على وقت كاف لقراءتها،
so just trust your gut.
لذا فقط ثقوا بحدسكم.
Poem 1: A lion roars and a dog barks. It is interesting / and fascinating
القصيدة 1: أسد يزأر .. وكلبٌ ينبح.. من مثير للاهتمام / والرئع
that a bird will fly and not / roar or bark. Enthralling stories about animals
أن العصفور سيطير ولن/ يزئر أو ينبح. توجد قصص مُشوقة عن الحيوانات
are in my dreams and I will sing them all if I / am not exhausted or weary.
في أحلامي وسأغني لهم جميعًا إن لم / أكن مُتعبا أو حزينا.
Poem 2: Oh! kangaroos, sequins, chocolate sodas! / You are really beautiful!
القصيدة 2: اوه! كنغر، ترتر ، شوكلاتة مشروبات غازية / أنت حقا جميل!
Pearls, / harmonicas, jujubes, aspirins! All / the stuff they've always talked about (...)
لآلئ، / هرمونيكا، العناب، أسبيرين! كل / الأشياء التي لطالما تحدثنا عنها (...)
Alright, time's up.
حسنًا، انتهى الوقت.
So if you think the first poem was written by a human,
إذن، إذا تعتقد أن القصيدة الأولى كتبها إنسان
put your hand up.
ارفع يدك.
OK.
حسنا.
And if you think the second poem was written by a human,
وإذا تعتقد أن القصيدة الثانية كتبها إنسان،
put your hand up.
ارفع يدك.
We have, more or less, a 50/50 split here.
حسنًا، لدينا تقريا نسبة 50/50 بالمئة.
It was much harder.
كان أمرًا صعبًا جدا.
The answer is,
الإجابة هي،
the first poem was generated by an algorithm called Racter,
كُتبت القصيدة الأولى باستخدام برنامج خوارزميات يُسمى "Racter"،
that was created back in the 1970s,
والذي تم إنشائه في السبعينات،
and the second poem was written by a guy called Frank O'Hara,
أما القصيدة الثانية فقد كتبها رجل يُدعى فرانك أوهارا،
who happens to be one of my favorite human poets.
والذي يصدف أنه من الشعراء المفضلين لدي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So what we've just done now is a Turing test for poetry.
إذن، ما قمنا به الآن هو اختبار "تورنج" للشعر.
The Turing test was first proposed by this guy, Alan Turing, in 1950,
تم اقتراح اختبار تورنج لأول مرة سنة 1950 من قبل شاب يدعى آلان تورنج،
in order to answer the question,
بهدف الإجابة عن سؤال،
can computers think?
هل يمكن للكمبيوتر أن يُفكر؟
Alan Turing believed that if a computer was able
يعتقد آلان تورنج إذ كان الكمبيوتر قادرًا
to have a to have a text-based conversation with a human,
على إجراء محادثة مبنية على نص مع إنسان،
with such proficiency such that the human couldn't tell
بمثل هذه الكفاءة حتى أن الإنسان لا يمكنه
whether they are talking to a computer or a human,
أن يُميز ما إذا كان يتحدث مع كمبيوتر أو مع إنسان،
then the computer can be said to have intelligence.
ثم بذلك يُمكننا أن نقول أن أجهزة الكمبيوتر تتمتع بنسبة ذكاء.
So in 2013, my friend Benjamin Laird and I,
إذن في سنة 2013، قمت أنا وصديقي بينجامين لايرد،
we created a Turing test for poetry online.
بوضع اختبار تورنج للشعرعلى الإنترنت.
It's called bot or not,
ويسمى "آلي أو لا"،
and you can go and play it for yourselves.
ويمكنكم أن تقوموا بتجربته بأنفسكم.
But basically, it's the game we just played.
ولكن بالأساس، هي اللعبة التي لعبناها منذ لحظات.
You're presented with a poem,
تُقدم لك قصيدة،
you don't know whether it was written by a human or a computer
وأنت لا تدري إن كتبها إنسان أو كمبيوتر
and you have to guess.
وعليك أن تُخمن.
So thousands and thousands of people have taken this test online,
وقام الآلاف والألاف من الأشخاص بإجراء هذا الاختبار على الإنترنت،
so we have results.
إذ لدينا النتائج.
And what are the results?
وماهي هذه النتائج؟
Well, Turing said that if a computer could fool a human
حسنًا، حسب "اختبار التورنج" إذا استطاع كمبيوت خداع إنسان
30 percent of the time that it was a human,
ويكون 30 بالمائة من الوقت إنسان،
then it passes the Turing test for intelligence.
وهكذا يجتاز اختبار "تورنج" للذكاء.
We have poems on the bot or not database
توجد قصائد في قاعدة بيانات "آلي أو لا"
that have fooled 65 percent of human readers into thinking
خدعت 65 بالمئة من القراء الذين ظنوا
it was written by a human.
أنها كتبت من قبل إنسان.
So, I think we have an answer to our question.
إذن، أعتقد أن لدينا إجابة على سؤالنا.
According to the logic of the Turing test,
وفقًا لمنطق اختبار "تورنج"،
can a computer write poetry?
هل يستطيع الكمبيوتر كتابة قصائد شعرية؟
Well, yes, absolutely it can.
حسنًا، نعم، بالطبع يستطيع.
But if you're feeling a little bit uncomfortable
ولكن إذا لم تقتنع بالكامل
with this answer, that's OK.
بهذه الإجابة، فهذا مقبول.
If you're having a bunch of gut reactions to it,
وإذا كانت غير مقتنع بالأمر،
that's also OK because this isn't the end of the story.
فهذا مقبول أيضًا لأن هذه ليست نهاية القصّة.
Let's play our third and final test.
دعونا نقوم بإجراء اختبارنا الثالث والأخير.
Again, you're going to have to read
مرة أخرى، عليك قراءة القصيدة
and tell me which you think is human.
وإخباري أيهما تظن أن كتبت من قبل إنسان.
Poem 1: Red flags the reason for pretty flags. / And ribbons.
القصيدة 1: الأعلام الحمراء هي السبب أن الأعلام جميلة. / والشرائط.
Ribbons of flags / And wearing material / Reasons for wearing material. (...)
شرائط من الأعلام / والمواد التي تُرتدى / أسباب من المواد التي تُلبس. (...)
Poem 2: A wounded deer leaps highest, / I've heard the daffodil
القصيدة 2: الأيل المجروح يقفز للأعلى / لقد سمعت النرجس البري
I've heard the flag to-day / I've heard the hunter tell; /
لقد سمعت العلم اليوم / لقد سمعت الصياد يقول،/
'Tis but the ecstasy of death, / And then the brake is almost done (...)
"تيس" لكن نشوة الموت وبعدها يكون الفاصل قد انتهى تقريبا. (...)
OK, time is up.
حسنًا، انتهى الوقت.
So hands up if you think Poem 1 was written by a human.
إذن، ارفع يدك إذا كنت تظن أن القصيدة 1 كتبها إنسان.
Hands up if you think Poem 2
ارفع يدك إذا كنت تظن أن القصيدة 2 كتبها إنسان.
Whoa, that's a lot more people.
أوو، عدد كبير من الأشخاص.
So you'd be surprised to find that Poem 1
سوف تتفاجؤن كون أن القصيدة الأولى
was written by the very human poet Gertrude Stein.
كتابتها شاعر بشري جدا يُدعى "جيرترود شتاين".
And Poem 2 was generated by an algorithm called RKCP.
وتمت كتابة القصيدة الثانية باستخدام برنامج خوارزمياتُ يُدعى RKCP.
Now before we go on, let me describe very quickly and simply,
والآن قبل أن نُكمل، دعوني أوضح لكم بسرعة وبطريقة سهلة،
how RKCP works.
كيفية عمل RKCP.
So RKCP is an algorithm designed by Ray Kurzweil,
إذن، RKCP هو خوارزمية صُممت من قبل "راي كورزويل"،
who's a director of engineering at Google
وهو مدير الهندسة في جوجل
and a firm believer in artificial intelligence.
وهو من أشد المؤمنين بمجال الذكاء الاصطناعي.
So, you give RKCP a source text,
إذن، تُعطي RKCP النص الأصلي،
it analyzes the source text in order to find out how it uses language,
إذ أنها تُحلل مصدر النص من أجل معرفة كيفية استخدام اللغة،
and then it regenerates language
ثم تُعيد صياغة الكلام
that emulates that first text.
لكي يتشابه مع النص الأصلي.
So in the poem we just saw before,
لذا، في القصيدة التي قمتم بقراءتها للتو،
Poem 2, the one that you all thought was human,
القصيدة الثانية، التي اعتقدتم أنها كُتبت من قبل إنسان،
it was fed a bunch of poems
تتكون من مجموعة قصائد شعرية
by a poet called Emily Dickinson
كُتبت من قبل شاعرة تُدعى "إميلي ديكنسون"
it looked at the way she used language,
فقد قامت باستيعاب طريقة استخدام اللغة،
learned the model,
وتعلمت المنهجية المتبعة،
and then it regenerated a model according to that same structure.
ثم أعادت صياغتها وفقًا لنفس التركيبة.
But the important thing to know about RKCP
ولكن أهم شيء في RKCP
is that it doesn't know the meaning of the words it's using.
أنها لا تعرف معنى الكلمات المستخدمة.
The language is just raw material,
فاللغة هي عبارة عن مواد أولية خامة،
it could be Chinese, it could be in Swedish,
يُمكن أن تكون لغة صينية، أو لغة سويدية،
it could be the collected language from your Facebook feed for one day.
يُمكن أن تكون اللغة التي تم جمعها من مُستجدات حسابك على الفايسبوك في يوم واحد.
It's just raw material.
إنها فقط مواد أولية.
And nevertheless, it's able to create a poem
وعلى الرغم من ذلك، RKCP قادر على كتابة قصيدة
that seems more human than Gertrude Stein's poem,
تبدو بشرية أكثر من قصائد "جيرترود شتاين"
and Gertrude Stein is a human.
مع العلم أن "جيرترود شتاين" إنسان.
So what we've done here is, more or less, a reverse Turing test.
إذن، ما قمنا به هنا، هو إجراء اختبار ترونج بشكل عكسي.
So Gertrude Stein, who's a human, is able to write a poem
إذن، "جيرترود شتاين"، إنسان، قادر على كتابة قصيدة
that fools a majority of human judges into thinking
قد خدعت معظم الناس وجعلتهم يظنون
that it was written by a computer.
أنها كُتبت من قبل كمبيوتر.
Therefore, according to the logic of the reverse Turing test,
بالتالي، وفقًا لمنطق اختبار الترونج المعكوس،
Gertrude Stein is a computer.
فإن "جيرترود شتاين" هو كمبيوتر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Feeling confused?
تشعرون بالحيرة؟
I think that's fair enough.
أظن أن ذلك عادل.
So far we've had humans that write like humans,
إلى حد الآن لدينا بشر يكتبون مثل البشر،
we have computers that write like computers,
ولدينا حواسيب تكتب مثل الحواسيب،
we have computers that write like humans,
وحواسيب تكتب مثل البشر،
but we also have, perhaps most confusingly,
وربما هو الأمر الغريب، إلا أنه هناك
humans that write like computers.
بشر يكتبون مثل الحواسيب.
So what do we take from all of this?
إذن، ما الذي نفهمه من هذا كله؟
Do we take that William Blake is somehow more of a human
هل نعتبر "ويليام بلايك" بطريقة ما أنه أكثر بشرية
than Gertrude Stein?
من "جيرترود شتاين"؟
Or that Gertrude Stein is more of a computer than William Blake?
أو"جيرترود شتاين" يتمتع بميزات كمبيوتر أكثر من "ويليام بلايك"؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
These are questions I've been asking myself
هذه أسئلة تدور في ذهني
for around two years now,
منذ حوالي سنتين إلى الآن،
and I don't have any answers.
وليس لدي أجوبة لها.
But what I do have are a bunch of insights
ولكن ما لدي هو مجموعة من التصورات
about our relationship with technology.
حول علاقتنا بالتكنولوجيا.
So my first insight is that, for some reason,
إذن، تصوري الأول، لسبب ما،
we associate poetry with being human.
جمعنا الشعر بصفتنا بشرا.
So that when we ask, "Can a computer write poetry?"
لذلك، عندما نطرح السؤال، "هل يستطيع الكمبيوتر كتابة الشعر؟"
we're also asking,
فنحن نسأل أيضًا،
"What does it mean to be human
"ماذا يعني أن نكون بشرا
and how do we put boundaries around this category?
وكيف يمكننا وضع حدود لهذه الفئة؟
How do we say who or what can be part of this category?"
كيف نقول من أو ما الذي يمكن أن يكون جزءا من هذه الفئة؟"
This is an essentially philosophical question, I believe,
هذا في الأساس سؤال فلسفي، في نظري،
and it can't be answered with a yes or no test,
ولا يُمكن الإجابة عنه باختبار نعم أو لا،
like the Turing test.
مثل اختبار تورنج.
I also believe that Alan Turing understood this,
وأعتقد أيضًا أن "آلان ترونج" فهم هذا،
and that when he devised his test back in 1950,
وذلك عندما أنشأ اختباره سنة 1950،
he was doing it as a philosophical provocation.
فقد كان يقوم بذلك كتحد فلسفي.
So my second insight is that, when we take the Turing test for poetry,
وتصوري الثاني كان، عندما جربنا اختبار تورنج للشعر،
we're not really testing the capacity of the computers
أننا لم نكن نختبر قدرة الحواسيب
because poetry-generating algorithms,
لأن خوارزميات إعادة صياغة الشعر،
they're pretty simple and have existed, more or less, since the 1950s.
بسيطة جدًا وموجودة تقريبًا منذ الخمسينات.
What we are doing with the Turing test for poetry, rather,
فعلى الأرجح، ما قُمنا به في اختبار الترونج للشعر،
is collecting opinions about what constitutes humanness.
يتمثل في جمع الآراء حول ما يُشكل الإنسان.
So, what I've figured out,
إذن، ما توصلنا إليه،
we've seen this when earlier today,
لقد رأينا ذلك في وقت سابق اليوم،
we say that William Blake is more of a human
ذكرنا أن "ويليام بلايك" أكثر بشرية
than Gertrude Stein.
من "جيرترود شتاين".
Of course, this doesn't mean that William Blake
بالطبع، هذا لا يعني أن "ويليام بلايك"
was actually more human
يتمتع بصفة بشرية بشكل أكثر
or that Gertrude Stein was more of a computer.
أو أن "جيرترود شتاين" يشبه أكثر جهاز كمبيوتر.
It simply means that the category of the human is unstable.
وهذا يعني ببساطة أن فئة البشر غير مستقرة.
This has led me to understand
وهذا ما أوصلني إلى فهم
that the human is not a cold, hard fact.
أن الإنسان ليس حقيقة صلبة باردة.
Rather, it is something that's constructed with our opinions
بل، هو حقيقة تتشكل مع آرائنا
and something that changes over time.
وتتغير مع الوقت.
So my final insight is that the computer, more or less,
وفي تصوري الأخير، أن الكمبيوتر، نوعا ما،
works like a mirror that reflects any idea of a human
يعمل مثل المرآة أي يعكس كل فكرة في ذهن شخص
that we show it.
نقوم بإظهارها.
We show it Emily Dickinson,
قدمنا له "إميلي ديكنسون"،
it gives Emily Dickinson back to us.
فأعاد لنا "إميلي ديكنسون".
We show it William Blake,
قدمنا له "ويليام بلايك"،
that's what it reflects back to us.
وذلك ما أعاد تقديمه لنا.
We show it Gertrude Stein,
قدمنا له "جيرترود شتاين"،
what we get back is Gertrude Stein.
وذلك ما أعاده لنا.
More than any other bit of technology,
أكثر من مجرد شيء في التكنولوجيا،
the computer is a mirror that reflects any idea of the human we teach it.
فإن الكمبيوتر مرآة تعكس أي فكرة تخطر على بال إنسان، قمنا بتعليمه إياها.
So I'm sure a lot of you have been hearing
لذلك، أنا متأكد أن الكثير منكم قد سمع
a lot about artificial intelligence recently.
مؤخرًا الكثير حول الذكاء الاصطناعي.
And much of the conversation is,
وتدور أكثر النقاشات حول
can we build it?
هل يُمكننا صنعه؟
Can we build an intelligent computer?
هل يمكننا صنع أجهزة كمبيوتر ذكية؟
Can we build a creative computer?
هل يمكننا صنع أجهزة كمبيوتر مُبدعة؟
What we seem to be asking over and over
والسؤال المتكرر جائما يتمحور حول
is can we build a human-like computer?
ما إذا كنا قادرين على بناء كمبيوتر يُشبه الإنسان؟
But what we've seen just now
ولكن ما أدركناه الآن
is that the human is not a scientific fact,
أن الإنسان ليس حقيقة علمية،
that it's an ever-shifting, concatenating idea
بل سلسلة من الأفكار التي تتغير دائمًا
and one that changes over time.
إضافة إلى تغيرها مع الوقت.
So that when we begin to grapple with the ideas
إذن، عندما بدأنا بالتمسك بأفكار
of artificial intelligence in the future,
الذكاء الاصطناعي في المستقبل،
we shouldn't only be asking ourselves,
فلا يجدر علينا أن نسأل أنفسنا فقط،
"Can we build it?"
"هل يُمكنا صنعه؟"
But we should also be asking ourselves,
بل علينا أن نسأل أنفسنا أيضًا،
"What idea of the human do we want to have reflected back to us?"
"ما هي الفكرة البشرية التي نريد أن نعكسها لأنفسنا؟"
This is an essentially philosophical idea,
فهي بالأساس فكرة فلسفية،
and it's one that can't be answered with software alone,
ولا يمكن الإجابة عنها ببرنامج كمبيوتر لوحده،
but I think requires a moment of species-wide, existential reflection.
بل أظن أن ذلك يتطلب لحظة من انعكاس وجودي، على نطاق متنوع وواسع.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)